A Finding Aid to the Adolf Dehn Papers, 1912-1987, in the Archives of American Art AAA.dehnadop
Archives of American Art
- Correspondence, circa 1919-1982; Series 2; (Boxes 1-4; 3.5 linear feet)
  - General and Personal Correspondence, circa 1919-1982; 2.1
    - U-V, circa 1936-1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Untermeyer, Louis
      Van Veem, Felicia
      Veltman, Joyce
      Vereisky, Orest
      Vroom, Peter
    - Woodul, Sallie, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 5-8)
    - W, circa 1931-1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Wakita, Kazu
      Weedon, Ella Howell
      Weinstein, Max
      Weithman, Joan
      Wengenroth, Stow
      West, Clifford
      Wilder, M.A.
      Wilke, Wyert[?]
      Wunderlich, Paul
    - Zigrosser, Carl, 1926-1966 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Zinker, Ann, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Z, circa 1960-1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Zecher, Alice
      Zellmer, Rev. N.W. (Nel)
      Zeitt, Elizabeth
      Zinders, Earl
      Zucker, Paul
      Zuckers, Jacques and Nina
    - First Name Only-"A-B,", circa 1960-1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - First Name Only-"C-I,", circa 1926-1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - First Name Only-"J-N,", circa 1920-1968 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - First Name Only-O-S, circa 1927-1968 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - First Name Only-V-Y, 1925, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Unidentified, circa 1920-1968 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Get Well Cards, circa 1968; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
    - Envelopes, circa 1919-1946 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Business Correspondence, circa 1923-1982; 2.2
    Business correspondence documents Dehn's career and professional associations. Files consist of letters from galleries, museum directors, collectors, publishers, researchers, greeting card companies, researchers, and government officials.
    Gallery correspondence includes exhibitions lists, consignment lists, sales invoices and accounts and records galleries from across the United States that sold Dehn's prints and watercolors. Business correspondence documents early representation of his work by the Weyhe Gallery and his long association with both Associated American Artists, an art gallery that marketed art, primarily prints, to the middle class; and American Artists Group, a greeting card company, an organization created to provide work for artists during the Depression by commissioning original artwork. Generally, correspondence from museums and universities contains information about exhibitions of Dehn's work.
    Files are arranged in alphabetical order by name of organization. Individuals, most of whom contacted Dehn to purchase prints or request information, are listed by their last names.
    - A. Lubin, Inc., circa 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - American Artists Group, 1943-1982; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
    - American Watercolor Society, 1955-1969 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Art Source, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Associated American Artists, 1936-1974 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
    - A, 1942-1973 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      A.B. Closson, Jr. Co.
      Abbott Laboratories
      Addison Gallery of American Art
      Allentown Art Museum
      Allied Publications, Inc.
      American Federation of Arts
      American Institute of Graphic Arts (AIGA)
      American National Red Cross
      Amon Carter Museum of Western Art
      Archives of American Art
      Argus Gallery
      Art Directors Club
      Art Museum of the New Britain Institute
      Art Students League of New York
      Associated Artists of Pittsburgh
      Audobon Artists
    - Boro Art Center, 1963-1968 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - B, 1950-1966 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      Bay Head Cultural Center
      Balfe, Jim
      Baltimore Museum of Art
      Birmingham Museum of Art
      Bisonte
      Book-of-the-Month Club
      Brooklyn Museum
      Brown and Bigelow
      Butler Institute of American Art
    - Carlin Galleries, circa 1962-1977; (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 32-35)
    - Century Association, circa 1959-1968 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Claire Fox Art Gallery, circa 1962-1967 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - C-D, 1941-1981 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      Capricorn Galleries
      Cargill, Incorporated
      Carnegie Institute
      Carter Travel Service
      Charles and Emma Frye Free Public Art Museum
      Charles E. Slatkin Galleries
      Chase Gallery
      Chemstrand
      Cincinnati Art Museum
      Clarkson N. Potter, Inc.
      Cleveland Museum of Art
      Clugston, Sue
      Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center
      Connecticut Mutual Life Insurance Company
      Copins, Edna
      Country Beautiful
      Cushing Galleries
      Daytons Department Store
      DePauw University (John Cain)
      Doeskin Products
      Drake, Lawrence
    - E-F, 1937-1968 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      Edmond et Jacques Desjobert
      Embassy of the United States - Athens, Greece
      Encyclopedia Britannica
      Estelle Mandel
      Famous Artists Schools
      Farrar and Rinehart
      Federal Support for the Visual Arts
      Fendrick Gallery
      Field Enterprises Educational Corporation
      Fine American Art Calendar Program
      Fine Arts Associates
      Finlandia Foundation
      Fireman's Fund American Insurance Companies
      Fischer, Rosamond
      Ford Foundation
      Fortune
      Frank Partridge Gallery of Contemporary Artists
    - Gallery 10, circa 1959-1967; (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 40-42)
    - Grinnell Galleries, 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - G, circa 1956-1966 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      Gallant, Mrs. W.E.
      Gallery of Modern Art
      General Theological Seminary
      Geo. Nix Gallery
      Gimbel Brothers
      Glassboro State College
      Granrud, Carl F.
      Grier, William H.
    - Heath Gallery, 1968-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - H, circa 1929-1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Haley, Anne
      Harmon Foundation
      Harry Salpeter Gallery, Inc.
      Hendrika Hobbelink Kaastra Gallery
      Houghton Mifflin Company
      Huntington Township Art League
    - I.F.A. Galleries, 1962-1964 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - International Graphic Arts Society (IGAS), 1961-1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - I-J, 1958-1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Indiana Bank and Trust Company
      International Art Publishing Co.
      Ithaca College
      J.J. Little and Ives Co.
      John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation
      John Price Jones Company
    - Kennedy Galleries, circa 1969-1975; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    - K-L, 1923, 1943-1970 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Keady, Joseph (G.J.)
      Kenneth W. Brooks, A.I.A.
      Ketterlinus Lithographic Manufacturing Company
      Kircher, Helton and Collett, Inc.
      Krasner Gallery
      Le Sueur Country Historical Society
      Lezius and Hiles Co.
      The Liberater
      Library of Congress
      Living American Art
      Look
      Loring's Art Gallery
      Louis Comfort Tiffany Foundation
      Louisiana State University
      Low, Sanford B.
      Lutheran Brotherhood
    - McKnight, Henry T., 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - M, 1945-1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Macy's New York
      Mark Twain Journal
      Maxwell Galleries
      McCormick, Madelaine
      Michigan State College
      Mickelson Gallery
      Milch Galleries
      Miller, Frank
      Minneapolis (City of)
      The Minneapolis Star and Tribune
      Minneapolis School of Art
      Minnetonka Center of Arts and Education
      Mitch Morse Gallery
      Montclair Art Museum
      Mostro Internazionale di Lugano di Bianco e Nero
      Mulert, Johan
      Museum of Modern Art, New York
    - National Academy of Design, 1960-1966 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1961-1968 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - N-O, circa 1939-1966 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      The Nation
      National Arts Club
      National Council of Jewish Women
      National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C.
      New Britain Museum of American Art
      New York Times (John Canaday)
      Newark Museum
      New York World's Fair
      Nina Kaiden Ruder and Finn
      O'Dwyer and Bernstien
      Office of the Postmaster, New York
      Ohio Expositions Commission
      Ohio State Fair
      Ohio University
      Optometric Center of New York
    - Print Club (Philadelphia), 1954-1977 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Print Council of America, 1957-1963 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - P-R, 1934-1974 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Pepsi-Cola
      Palm Springs Desert Museum
      Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts
      Peter M. David Gallery
      Philadelphia Art Alliance
      Philadelphia Museum of Art
      Pratt Center for Contemporary Printmaking
      Prentice-Hall
      Print Club of Rochester
      Rochester Art Center
      Rockefeller University
      Rosenwald, Lessing J.
      Roth and Riseman
      Rudolph Galleries
    - Society of American Graphic Artists, 1948-1972 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - State of New York - Department of Taxation and Finance, 1955-1960 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Studio North, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - S, 1951-1967 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      Sachs Quality Stores
      St. Peter's Episcopal Church
      Seward, William W.
      Sigmund Freud Archives, New York
      Smithsonian Institution
      Stamford Museum and Nature Center
      State Historical Society of Missouri
      Staten Island Institute of Arts and Sciences
      Styline
      Syracuse University
    - Tahir Gallery, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - T-U, 1949-1966 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      Temple University
      Thieme, Lillian B.
      UNESCO
      University of Maine
      University of Minnesota
      Union Tipografica Editorial Hispano Americana (UTEHA)
    - United States Department of State, 1949-1964 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - United States Gypsum Company, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - United States Information Agency, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - University of Missouri, 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Veltman Gallery, 1960-1964 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Vera Lazuk Gallery, circa 1952-1968; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 28-29)
    - Viking Press, 1953-1972 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - V-Y, 1947-1966 (Box 4, Folder 31)
      Verlag Mensch und Arbeit
      Village Art Center
      Voice of American
      Wadsworth Atheneum
      Wagner College
      Waldemar Medical Research Foundation
      Walker Art Center
      WCET
      Weddige, Emil
      Werner, Alfred
      Who's Who
      Woodmere Art Festival
      World Biography
      York Art Center
  - Virginia Dehn Correspondence, 1968-1979; 2.3
    Files consist of the general, personal and business correspondence of Virginia Dehn. General A-Z correspondence includes both personal letters, including notes her sister-in-law Viola Tiala recalling Dehn's early years and business letters, primarily from galleries and museums concerning her or her late husband's art work. There are separate files of condolence letters and cards received from friends and associates. Additionally there are several files of correspondence with the University of Missouri Press related to the publication of a book on the prints and drawings of Adolf Dehn, which includes signed contracts and third-party correspondence with Dehn collectors.
    While additional Virginia Dehn correspondence is scattered throughout the other correspondence subseries, this grouping was established, presumably by the creator, and has been retained. General correspondence is arranged alphabetically; insurance and University of Missouri Press correspondence is arranged chronologically; and condolence cards and letters are in no specific order.
    - General A-Z, 1966-1979; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 31-32)
      Artists Equity Association
      Bohrod, Aaron
      Chelsea Art Festival
      Constantine, Mildred
      Dasburg, Al and Ann
      Eastern States Art Exhibition
      Fiene, Ernest
      Gareck, Mr. and Mrs. Robert
      Granrud, Carl
      International Exhibitions Foundation
      Larcada Gallery
      Lewis
      Oehlschlaeger, Everett
      Ogg, Oscar
      Perls, Frank
      Phamp, Evelyn
      Pope, Mrs. John
      Preventive Medicine Institute-Strang Clinic
      Smith, Kim
      Solomon, Elke
      Sussman, Bonnie K.
      Tiala, Violet
      Zigrosser, Carl
    - General - First Names Only, circa 1966-1974 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Condolence Letters, 1968; (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 34-37)
    - Condolence Cards, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Insurance Companies, 1968-1979 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - University of Missouri Press, 1968-1976; (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 40-43)
    - University of Missouri Press - Insurance, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Writings, circa 1920-1971; Series 3; (Boxes 4-5; 0.25 linear feet)
  Found in this series are manuscripts, typescripts, and author's proofs of works written by Dehn and others. The bulk of this series consists of professional writings by Dehn including a drafts of articles on watercolor paintings and techniques for the Encyclopedia Britannica; the typescript and author's proof's for his book Watercolor, Gouache, and Casein Painting (1955); and profiles of artists Alois Lang and Boardman Robinson. Writings by others include a draft for Adolf Dehn Drawings, which was published by the University of Missouri Press, as well as poetry attributed to Eileen Hall Lake.
  Files in this series are arranged alphabetically by title; supplied titles and author attributions were derived from creator's file titles. The Writing series is arranged into two subseries:
  Subseries 3.1: Writings, circa 1920-1968
  Subseries 3.2: Writings by Others, circa 1924-1971
  - Writings, circa 1920-1968; 3.1
    - "Boardman Robinson as I Know Him", circa 1952-1968 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Famous Artists School - Painting Techniques, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - "Looking for E. Dreams,", undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - "Portrait of Alois Lang at Oberammergau,", circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - "Technique" for Encyclopedia Britannica, circa 1955 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Watercolor, Gouache, and Casein Painting, 1954-1955; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 50-51)
    - "Watercolor Painting in the United States" for Encyclopedia Britannica, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Writings by Others, circa 1924-1971; 3.2
    - Adolf Dehn Drawings by Virginia Dehn, circa 1970-1971; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 53-54)
    - Art Criticism (about Dehn), circa 1940-1968 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Poems by Eileen Hall Lake, circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Poetry Journal (attributed to Eileen Hall Lake), 1924-1936 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Financial Records, 1936-1965; Series 4; (Box 5; 0.45 linear feet)
  Found in this series are invoices and receipts, the bulk of which are from Associated American Artists, which document works on consignment, artist account information, as well as receipts for framing and photography services, There is also a file of travel related receipts and another of receipts for medical treatment. Federal and state income tax returns for the years 1940-1942 are also included in this series.
  Documents are arranged by in chronological order by type.
  - Invoices and Receipts (Associated American Artists), 1937-1947; (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
  - Invoices and Receipts, 1936-1965; (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - State and Federal Income Tax Returns, 1940-1942 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Printed Materials, circa 1915-1987; Series 5; (Boxes 5-6; 1.2 linear feet)
  Items in this series include exhibition announcements, catalogs, brochures, clippings, article reprints, programs, and other publications. There are also examples of Dehn's commercial work, including Christmas cards, calendars featuring Dehn's watercolor scenes, and a sample of wallpaper, as well as reproductions of his fine art work.
  Exhibitions announcements and catalogs are for one-man exhibitions and group shows that featured his art, with scattered announcements and catalogs for other artists work, including his wife Virginia Dehn. Catalogs and announcements from Associated American Artists document limited edition prints, Christmas cards, and other object by their artist members that were available for sale. Included was a catalog of Dehn prints and portfolios to mark his twenty fifth year as a celebrated printmaker; this catalog is a source of valuable information about Dehn's print oeuvre as it includes image, titles, creation dates, plate dimensions and prices. There is also announcements and brochures from The Adolf Dehn Print Club, a print society established by the artist in 1934 to promote and distribute his work.
  Clippings are primarily about Dehn and his work, but there are also scattered articles on other artists, art criticism and general news items. Publications include two issues of Improvisations, a journal published in conjunction with the Artists Equity Associations annual Spring Fantasia, in which the artists contributed illustrations for sympathetic advertisers and a book of poetry by Mura Dehn, the artists first wife.
  Other printed materials found in this series include publishers catalogs that contained books illustrated by Dehn, art school brochures and newsletters from programs at which Dehn taught or attended, event programs, and an annotated insurance company calendar. Additional printed materials can be found in Dehn's scrapbooks.
  Items have been grouped together by document type; within files documents are in rough chronological order.
  - Adolf Dehn Print Club Materials, circa 1934-1937 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Announcements and Catalogs - Associated American Artists, crica 1940s-1979; (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1924-1982; (7 folders) (Box 5, Folder 11-17)
  - Exhibition Annoucements and Catalogs - Virginia Dehn, 1961-1980 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - General Catalogs and Programs, circa 1922-1970 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Art School Brochures and Newletters, 1942-1971 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Ephemera, circa 1930, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Commercial Work, 1950-1968 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, circa 1950 and undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Magazine Clippings, circa 1929-1977 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Magazine Clippings - The Minne-Ha-Ha, 1915-1916 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Newspaper Clippings, circa 1920-1970; (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 26-28)
  - Improvisions, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Improvisions, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Lion Tamer and Other Poems by Mura Dehn, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Object: Every American an Art Patron, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Red Cartoons from the Daily Worker, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Scrapbooks, 1912-1968; Series 6; (Boxes 6-7: 0.5 linear feet)
  This series consists of three scrapbooks. One scrapbook contains clippings of editorial cartoons by Dehn's mentor and friend, the artist Boardman Robinson; the other two scrapbooks contain clippings, editorial cartoons, and exhibition announcements related to Dehn. Additionally there are several files of loose items that have become separated from the scrapbooks that contained them. There is a file of loose items that has been labeled "Extra Items from Scrapbook," a title provided by an earlier processor for a discrete group of documents that consist of a handwritten biographical note, photographs, and clippings. It is not known which scrapbook originally contained these items.
  One of the Dehn scrapbooks (Scrapbook I) is comprised of large loose sheets on which clippings, editorial cartoons, telegrams, programs, and exhibition announcements have been affixed. Included among the files of loose items are two early ink drawings of Gibson Girls by Dehn, posters, examples of his Christmas cards, as well as additional clippings and exhibition announcements.
  The other scrapbook (Scrapbook II) contains similar items, the bulk of which have remained affixed to the pages. Although unbound, the pages are stored within the front and back covers. Dehn's faded monogram is visible on the front cover. This scrapbook begins with a high school graduation announcement from 1914 and contains clippings and exhibition announcements that span from that early date to 1942. It also includes a loose 1929 announcement from the Weyhe Gallery, which contains a brief note to his mother and sister reporting early sales of his work form the exhibition.
  Additional clippings, exhibition announcements, as well as examples of Dehn's editorial cartoons, magazine covers, and Christmas card designs can be found in the Printed Materials series.
  The large sheets of Scrapbook I, as well as oversize loose items, have been arranged in rough chronological order. The clippings and other detached items from Scrapbook I have been arranged by format and date into several standard sized files. Due to the presence of adhesive residue, these files are heavily interleaved.
  - Scrapbook - Boardman Robinson Editorial Cartoons, 1912-1914 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook I, circa 1912-1945; (Comprised of loose oversize sheets, distributed amongst 6 folders, located in Box 7) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook I - Loose Items, circa 1912-1945; (6 folders; oversize loose items are located in Box 7) (Box 6, Folder 8-13)
  - Scrapbook II, circa 1914-1942; (Oversize scrapbook is located in Box 7) (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Extra Items from Scrapbook, circa 1917-1968 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Oversize Scrapbook I Sheets and Loose Items, circa 1912-1945; (related items located in Box 6, Folders 8-13) (Box 7 (sol))
  - Oversize Scrapbook II, circa 1914-1942 (Box 7 (sol))
- Artwork, circa 1920-1945; Series 7; (Box 6; 3 folders)
  This series contains sketches and artwork by Dehn and others. Items include 4 sketches attributed to Adolf Dehn; graphite and ink sketches attributed to Eileen Hall Lake, which were originally stored with her poetry journal that can be found in the subseries Writings by Others; and an etching by S.W. Hayter.
  Artwork files are arranged in alphabetical order by the artist's last name.
  - Sketches attributed to Adolf Dehn, 1929-1935 and undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Etching by S.W. Hayter, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Sketches attributed to Eileen Hall Lake, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Photographs, circa 1912-1961; Series 8; (Boxes 6 and 8; 8 folders)
  Photographs in this series include a vintage gelatin silver print portrait of Adolf Dehn by André Kertész;, vintage photographs of Dehn with family members; Dehn with friends, including Lawrence Barnett, Federico Castellon, Albert Christ-Janer; with his former wife Mura; two sets of photobooth photographs taken on separate occasions with Eileen Hall Lake and Willis Bock; and a series of photographs of Adolf and Virginia taken at Atelier Desjobert. Many of these vintage photographs are annotated on the verso. There is also a panoramic view of Camp Wadsworth, Spartenburg, South Carolina, where Dehn was detained as a conscientious objector of World War I. Also found are several photographic reproductions of Dehn's drawings, lithographs, and watercolors.
  - Adolf Dehn Portrait by André Kertész, circa 1928; (copy print and negative in folder; matted vintage print is located in Box 8) (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Adolf Dehn Portraits, circa 1920-1950; (2 vintage portraits) (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Adolf Dehn Alone and With Others, circa 1912-1961; (97 vintage photographs) (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Willis Bock Portraits, circa 1930s; (4 studio portraits of Willis Bock) (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Eileen Hall Lake and others, circa 1934-1943; (27 photographs) (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Etta Lee, Yo-Hay-Tong, and Unidentified People, circa 1920s-1930s; (6 photographs) (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Panoramic View of Camp Wadsworth, Spartanburg, South Carolina, 1918; (Oversize photograph torn in 4 pieces; located in Box 7) (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, circa 1929-1958; (16 photographs) (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Oversize Adolf Dehn Portrait by André Kertész, circa 1928 (Box 8)
  - Oversize Panoramic View of Camp Wadsworth, Spartanburg, South Carolina, 1918 (Box 8)